<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians desire, shewing, how and for what causes a man may desire death. / By William Houghton, preacher at Bicknor in Kent.</title>
            <author>Houghton, William, preacher at Bicknor in Kent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E602_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206406</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865567</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865567</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165632</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74852)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165632)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E602[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians desire, shewing, how and for what causes a man may desire death. / By William Houghton, preacher at Bicknor in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Houghton, William, preacher at Bicknor in Kent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Daniel, for Samuel Cartwright, at the signe of the Bible in Duck-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165632:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS DESIRE, SHEWING, How and for what Cauſes a man may deſire Death.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM HOUGHTON,</hi> Preacher at <hi>Bicknor</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t prima deſideria ſanctorum antiquae legis in primo Chriſti termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur adventu: ſic quoque modo deſideria ſanctorum novae legis in ſecundo Chriſti adventu, qui perfectam nobis beatitudinem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feret, deſinent.</p>
               <bibl>Auguſt.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <p>HINC LVCEM ET POCVLA SACRA</p>
               <p>ALMA MATER CANTA BRIGIA</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Roger Daniel,</hi> for <hi>Samuel Cartwright,</hi> at the Signe of the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Duck-lane.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:165632:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165632:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right VVorſhipfull Sir <hi>EDWARD WORTLEY,</hi> and his Religious Lady, my honoured Friends.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſires are the trueſt effigies of the mind: If a man be Heavenly, he hath heavenly deſires; if out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things terminate his deſires, he hath but an earthly mind, and no more then what <hi>Paul</hi> calls <hi>the ſpirit of the world:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Such mens deſires the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaks of, when he ſaith, <hi>Who will ſhew us any good,</hi> that is, matter of gain, and profit?<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.8.</note> But the godly mans deſire is thus ſet forth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.23.</note> 
               <hi>The deſire of our ſoul is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thy name, and to the remembrance of thee. There is none that I deſire upon earth, beſides thee.</hi> The worldlings deſire is to <hi>live many dayes</hi> and years upon earth: the godly mans deſire, <hi>that Chriſt may be in him,</hi> while he is here;<note place="margin">Luk. 12.29.</note> and <hi>that he may be with Chriſt,</hi> when he departs hence: and theſe (as <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines) <hi>are the beſt deſires:</hi> Worldly deſires at laſt give no ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing content to a mans ſoul; but, theſe are ſatisfying deſires: thoſe are oft fruſtrated, and come to nothing: but of theſe it is ſaid, <hi>God will fulfill the deſire of them that fear him.</hi> When a whole Kingdome is in a ſhaking condition, the deſires of many muſt needs fail;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heb. 12.28.</note> but the Chriſtians deſire is upon <hi>a Kingdome that cannot be ſhaken.</hi> My end and aim in ſending abroad this Sermon, is to 01
<pb facs="tcp:165632:3"/>increaſe theſe holy deſires in as many as ſhall read it. It is but a plain and unpoliſht piece: ſuch as it is I preſent it to your hands, as a ſmall return of thankfullneſſe for thoſe many favours I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from you; hoping it will find the better acceptance, becauſe I have known you many years, and that your deſires are ſet on the beſt things: Praying for your proſperity, and for all that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to you, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord Jeſus, <hi>William Houghton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165632:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Philip. 1.23.</bibl>
                  <p>Deſiring to be diſsolved, and to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aul</hi> (as you may ſee in this Chapter) ſtands at a certain doubt with himſelf, whether he ſhould live or die; live he would, that he might glorifie God; die, to be with Chriſt. The words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in them two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Paul</hi>'s deſire to be with Chriſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Having a deſire,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The reaſon of it; becauſe <hi>it is beſt of all.</hi> The Greek is moſt emphaticall, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Which is farre better;</hi> or as if one ſhould Engliſh it, <hi>Much more better.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 2.29.</note> 
               <hi>Simeon</hi> deſired to die, becauſe he had ſeen the Lords Chriſt: <hi>Paul</hi> here, that he might ſee Chriſt, and be for ever with him. <hi>Simeon</hi>'s word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Paul</hi>'s, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there is no materiall difference between them.<note place="margin">Vid. Sculter. Exercit. 156.</note> The former, according to the mind of the learned, ſignifies a dimiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to be fairly diſmiſt, and ſuffered to depart: the latter, to be let looſe, as mariners, when they let looſe and lanch forth. Or it may ſignifie to return: as, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Luke 12.36.</note> 
               <hi>When he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from the wedding.</hi> The firſt ſenſe may imply thus much, that the body is the ſouls priſon, wherein it is kept till it be ſent forth, and ſuffered to depart. The ſecond addes chains or coards wherein it is held till it be let looſe. The third, that this life is a place of exile, and the ſoul herein a pilgrim, till it return to God that gave it. But not to ſtand ſtraining of metaphors, when he ſaith, <hi>He deſired to depart, or be diſſolved,</hi> it is as much as if he had ſaid, That he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to die. Now conſider who it was that thus deſired death, <hi>Paul,</hi> a moſt zealous man, the Spirit of God calls him an <hi>elect
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165632:4"/>veſſel; Chryſoſtome,</hi> an <hi>heavenly man,</hi> or, if ye will (ſaith he) <hi>an earthly Angel:</hi> yet he ſeeks death, he <hi>deſires to be diſſolved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee then,<note place="margin">Act. 9.15. <hi>Doct.</hi>
               </note> That all muſt die, the beſt that are; the greateſt and holieſt muſt taſte of death: young men die as well as old: we ſee ſhort graves as well as long: rich men die as well as poore. It is ſaid in the Goſpel, <hi>that the beggar died:</hi> and preſently it is added, <hi>the rich man alſo dyed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16.22.</note> 
               <hi>And wiſe men die, as well as the fooliſh:</hi> nay,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49 10.</note> holy men too; <hi>Adam</hi> is called <hi>the ſon of God; Abraham, the friend of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 3.38.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes, the man of God;</hi> the Virgin <hi>Mary, the mother of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 2.23.</note> 
               <hi>David,</hi> was <hi>a man after Gods own heart: John Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 93. tit.</note> 
               <hi>a burning and ſhining light:</hi> yet they are all dead and gone,<note place="margin">Luc. 1.43.</note> and deſcended into the <hi>ſlimy pit,</hi> as the Prophet calls it: ſo that howſoever there may be a difference here amongſt men, yet then,<note place="margin">Abierunt, obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</note> all ſhall be alike.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> For firſt, thus hath God decreed, <hi>Statutum eſt</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) It is a Statute-law, a thing decreed in the high Court of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> and muſt needs ſtand faſt what is there determined.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, God doth fufter this, even the beſt and holyeſt to taſte of death, becauſe he will have them conformable to their head, even Jeſus Chriſt, who died for us.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Thirdly, becauſe of the mortality of men, and the nature of their condition here on earth: all men are of one matter, the godly are not made of one matter, and the wicked, of another, but all of one common matter, the duſt of the earth; according to that, <hi>Duſt thou art, and unto duſt thou ſhalt return;</hi> though while we live here, one be higher then another, yet then, there is an equality: as it is in caſting account, one counter ſtands for a thouſand, another for an hundred; but put them together into the bag, and one is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then another: or, as it is in a play, one bears the perſon of a King, another of a Knight, another of a Beggar, and very buſie they are; but when the play is done, every man goes to his own place. Thus it is with men; one may ſtand here in a higher room then another: but death makes him equall with the meaneſt: and if yee look into the ſame grave, after twenty or thirty years, you ſhall find no difference between the duſt of a King, and a beggar.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> Laſtly, this comes to paſſe becauſe of ſin, the proper cauſe of death; this poyſons our natures, and continually cleaves to us: as it was with <hi>Gehazi,</hi> this was his ſentence, <hi>That the Leproſie ſhould cleave to him and to his poſterity for ever:</hi> So ſin cleaves cloſe to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165632:4"/>us, till the day of our death: And as the Ivy ſticks ſo cloſe to the wall, that you cannot get it out, unleſſe you pull the wall it ſelf down: ſo ſin will not be had out of us, till the earthly houſe of this Tabernacle be diſſolved.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But, what difference then is there between the death of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the wicked?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Magnum diſcrimen,</hi> a great difference. For, God hath ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that death to wicked men ſhall be a paſſage to miſery; but it is altered to the godly, to them it is a paſſage to happineſſe; for to them, the ſting of it is taken away, therefore they need not to fear it, it can do them no hurt. Even as when you ſee a ſnake or ſerpent, its ſting being drawn out, you may play with it, put it in your boſome, it cannot hurt you: ſo may we entertain death, the ſting being taken away. Even as through the ſame gate, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned perſon is led out to execution, but the honeſt Citizen walks out for his pleaſure and recreation: ſo through the ſame gate of Death, wicked men paſſe to the torments of hell, but the godly to the paradiſe of heaven. As it is with one that goes over a bridge to a fair medow: ſo death is as it were a bridge to bring the ſaints to heaven. As <hi>Moſes</hi> from the top of mount Piſgah had a ſight of Canaan before he died:<note place="margin">Deut, 34.1.</note> ſo when the Saints and ſervants of God are ready to dye, they can ſee heaven before they depart this world: or as the Iſraelites, having travelld fourty years in the wilderneſſe, being now come to Jordan, they could look over it, and ſee the land of Canaan; they had no more to do, but to paſſe over the foard, and they were in the Land which flowed with milk and honey: ſo the people of God, when they have lived fourty or three-ſcore years, in the wilderneſſe of this world, and are come to die, they are onely to paſſe over the foard of death, and then they are in the land of promiſe. Thus you ſee, that howſoever all die, yet the death of all is not alike;<note place="margin">Num. 23.10.</note> 
               <hi>Oh let me dye the death of the righteous</hi> (ſaid that wizard <hi>Balaam</hi>) <hi>and let my laſt end be like his:</hi> ſhewing plainly, that the death of righteous and wicked men, in regard of their future eſtate, do exceedingly differ; alike they may be in their death, but they ſhall be unlike to each other after death.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> Now for the uſe of this; Is it ſo? muſt all dye? Let us then aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our ſelves of this, and not onely ſay we are mortall, as all men will ſay ſo, but ſeriouſly think of it; think that God may take us away this day, this hour, this may be the laſt word I may
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165632:5"/>ſpeak, the laſt word that ye may hear; therefore let us think of it ſeriouſly, that ſo <hi>we may apply our hearts to wiſdome:</hi> let us live every day, as if it were our laſt day: The life of man, how long ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, is but a life of ſeven dayes, which are multiplyed and run in a courſe: Now as a man that hath ſeven ſervants to ſerve him, if he be told that one of thoſe ſeven will kill him, narrowly obſerves every one of them, when they come by courſe to ſerve him: ſo man, whoſe life runs upon ſeven dayes in the week, which ſerve him by courſe, ſince one of them will certainly make an end of him; he ſhould therefore watch every day, ſaying to it, as <hi>John</hi> to <hi>Chriſt, Art thou he that ſhould come? or do I yet look for another?</hi> ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe muſt come, and death muſt come, nothing ſo ſure; how are we provided for their coming? When ſickneſſe is upon us, we can do nothing for extremity of pain; and therefore now, when the marrow is in our bones, and blood in our veins, let us think of it; and earneſtly prepare our ſelves for death. Now for the main Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>I deſire ſaith he to be diſſolved, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>A Chriſtian may lawfully deſire death:</hi> Its lawfull, nay neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſometimes to deſire death. Now when I ſay, that a man may deſire it, it is a great height this, and all attain not thereunto: for, death (ſaith the Philoſopher) is the moſt terrible of terribles,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Job 18.14.</note> 
               <hi>the King of fears,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> calls it: when a man ſhall ſeriouſly take to heart, and conſider that his ſoul muſt be ſeparated from his body, thoſe two old friends part and go aſſunder; ſome doubting and fear will ariſe through our frailty, and the beſt may have temptations in that kind: we know this, that when a man is to change his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, it puts him to trouble, if it be but into the next Shire, or the next town, every remove is troubleſome: when therefore the ſoul ſhall depart as far from the tabernacle of the body, as heaven from earth, there may be ſome trouble at this great remove; yet there is ſomething overcomes this trouble, whereby the Saints are willing to embrace death, and deſirous of a diſſolution. Would you ſee examples for it? <hi>Paul</hi> here in my Text, comes in with his <hi>cupio diſſolvi;</hi> and <hi>Simeon</hi> with his <hi>Nunc dimittis;</hi> the old man had long waited for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and now, when he had ſeen him, <hi>Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>let thy ſervant depart in peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 2.29.</note> 
               <hi>he had ſeen ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> beheld <hi>Chriſt</hi> with a ſpirituall, as well as with his corporal eyes; held him in the arms of his faith, as well as with the arms of his body: and now the world would no longer away with him, <hi>Let me depart</hi> (ſaith he) let me be gone. But before I come to ſhew
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165632:5"/>what ſhould move us to deſire death; I will ſpeak a few things by way of caution, and to prevent miſtakes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cautions. </seg>
               </label> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is this, That this deſire muſt alwayes be with ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the will of God; we muſt ſay as Chriſt, <hi>Let this cup paſſe, or come, as thy will and pleaſure is; not my will, but thy will be done.</hi> If it be the will of Chriſt that <hi>Peter</hi> go,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.39.</note> and <hi>John</hi> tarry ſtill;<note place="margin">Joh. 2 1.22.</note> they muſt both ſubmit to it: So muſt we, for the time and manner of our death, ſubmit our ſelves to God: our wills are never right but when they are conformable to the will of God. Thats the firſt, the reſt will follow upon it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As in the ſecond place; That it is no good deſire, to deſire death merely to be rid of anguiſh and pain: For, what if it be the will of God to hold us long under the rod; we muſt learn to kiſſe his holy hand that ſmites us: he doth it for the tryall of our faith, and other graces; and therefore we ought to bear it patiently. Thus much we may learn from <hi>Pauls</hi> example, who ſaith here, <hi>he deſired to be diſſolved,</hi> but it was not meerly to be rid of pain, ſo himſelf tels us, <hi>bonds and afflictions</hi> waited for him in every place, yet he made no reckoning of them, as you may ſee, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.21. and 23. compared together. Many a man would be ready to break priſon, but to be looſed from ſuch bonds, that is, iron bonds or chains: but <hi>Paul</hi> gloried in theſe, yet cryes out of the chains of his ſinnes, and wiſheth himſelf looſed from them; <hi>Oh miſerable man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of death?</hi> he doth not ſay, oh miſerable man, how am I afflicted?<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> I am in deaths oft, who ſhall deliver me from this death of the body? but, <hi>who ſhall deliver me from this body of death?</hi> This, this is it which makes many a godly Chriſtian even to ſigh and groan within himſelf, longing for a diſſolution, that ſo the body of ſin might be wholly deſtroyed; who yet is willing patiently to bear any croſſe his heavenly Father ſhall lay upon him, to render him conformable to his head Chriſt: and therefore they do very ill, and ſhew that they have not learnt that ſelf-denyall that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Chriſtians; who aſſoon as they begin to be afflicted in their bodies or eſtates, preſently call for death to come and take them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. It was <hi>Jonas</hi> fault, <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that thou wouldeſt take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my life from me:</hi> he comes in a pelting chafe,<note place="margin">Jonah 4.3.8.</note> in a pettiſh hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: So, many when they are croſt of their wills, wiſh with him they were out of the world, that they were dead, and laid in their graves, who (God knowes) are but badly prepared, and would be found in an ill caſe, ſhould death come indeed. Therefore let this be a ſecond Caution.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:165632:6"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, this deſire muſt never cauſe us to uſe any means to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten our death. I have read of one <hi>Hegeſias,</hi> a Philoſopher, of that eloquence and power in perſwading, that when he was pleaſed to repreſent before his auditours the miſeries of this life, his words ſtruck ſuch an impreſſion in them, that many of them went and made away themſelves. And in <hi>Hollingſheads</hi> Chronicles, theres a ſtory of a great man in this Kingdome, who in the times of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons wars, being much perplext in his mind, calld the Keeper of his Park to him, told him, he feared his Deer were ſtolen, charged him every night to go into the woods, to walk his rounds, and if he ſpied any man that would not ſtand at the firſt word, to ſhoot him: ſome two or three nights after (out of the depth of melancholly, (the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, that Prince of darkneſſe, working upon that black humour) he himſelf roſe out of his bed, went into his Park, the keeper ſpying him, calld to him, and bid him ſtand; he anſwered not, but walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on amongſt the trees, the Keeper took his Croſſe-bow, and ſhot his own Lord dead in the place: thus he fell by his own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and procured his own death by the hand of his Keeper. And if reports,<note place="margin">Lucernam non extinguebant, ſed ultro conſumi. Plut. Q. Rom. 468. Et tibi Publi, &amp; piis omnibus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinendus eſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus in cuſtodia corporis, nec in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſlu ejus à quo ille eſt nobis da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ex hominum vita migrandum eſt, ne munus hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum aſſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum à Dco, defu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſſe videamini. Somn. Scip.</note> or papers may be credited, ſome have been brought to the ſame paſſe by reaſon of the ſore preſſure of our late troubles. Now when I ſay, that a man may deſire death, it is far from my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that a man ſhould bring it upon himſelf in any ſuch way: grace teacheth us not to offer violence to nature: and therefore, as amongſt the Romans, the lights of the Temple were not to be put out, but ſuffered to burn as long as they laſted: ſo this candle of our lives muſt not be extinguiſht, till it conſume and go out of it ſelf, or till God ſhall require it in the defence of ſome lawfull cauſe: we muſt retain the ſoul in the cuſtody of the body, it muſt not be forced out of it, till he that gave it, call for it; leſt we ſhould ſeek to forſake that office and imployment which God hath aſſigned us. This is a third Caution.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, we ought alſo to conſider, that this is a kind of mixt deſire: as you may ſee here in S. <hi>Paul,</hi> he deſires death, becauſe it was ſo advantageous to him: yet is content to ſtay, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Gods people; <hi>To ſtay</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is more expedient for you, but for my ſelf, I deſire rather to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better:</hi> heres you ſee a mixture of deſires, this is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one way, that, another; for their private advantage, Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren deſire to be in heaven; for the benefit of others, they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſtay ſtill in this world. It is with them in this caſe, as it is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165632:6"/>with a chaſt and loving wife, her husband being gone from home, ſhe deſires his coming home; yet thinks ſometimes, oh that my husband would not come yet, till ſuch a buſineſſe be diſpatched, ſuch a room dreſt, and made ready for his coming, therefore keeps her ſelf doing, that nothing may offend the eye of her Lord when he comes and brings his gueſts with him: So the godly Chriſtian de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires the coming of Chriſt above all, <hi>Oh that thou wouldeſt rent the heavens and come down: Come Lord Jeſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 64.1.</note> 
               <hi>come quickly:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 22.20.</note> but becauſe he knowes not what hour his Lord will come in deed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he buſies himſelf in preparing and making all ready againſt his coming. It is written of <hi>Ortelius</hi> that great Coſmographer, that in his declining age, he ſet up the Globe of the world in his Study,<note place="margin">Bucolch. chron. 803.</note> with this inſcription, <hi>Contemno, &amp; orno, mente, manu:</hi> with his heart he contemnd the world, though with his hand he adornd it. This Embleme may teach us our duty; Let us ſeek to adorn the world by the works of our hands, let us endeavour what we can that the world might be bettered by us, while we live in it; yet let the world be in no eſteem with us: let our minds ſit looſe from the world, ready to leave it, whenſoever the Lord ſhall call us: and this is that we may learn out of that heavenly prayer of Chriſt, <hi>They are not of the world, even as I am not of the world; I pray not that thou ſhouldſt take them out of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 17.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>but that thou ſhouldſt keep them from the evil.</hi> In which words he meets with an Objection.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Might ſome ſay, If the Saints be not of this world, as Chriſt is not of this world; why do they not then follow Chriſt? he is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the world, why do not they go along with him?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Oh no: They muſt ſtay their time, they muſt not go yet, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I will not have them preſently taken out of the world,</hi> they ſhall ſtay a while to wraſtle with their corruptions, to preach the Goſpel to the world: that done, <hi>I will receive them to my ſelf.</hi> Verſ. 24. he ſaith, <hi>Father, I will that thoſe whom thou haſt given me, be with me:</hi> yet here he ſaith, <hi>I pray not that thou ſhouldſt take them out of the world;</hi> that is, not yet. Conformable to this will of Chriſt, is the will and deſire of the Saints: they deſire to be with Chriſt (for where ſhould the ſervant be, but with his Lord? the members, but with their head? the ſpouſe, but in the boſome of the bridegroome?) they deſire therefore I ſay, as the top of all their happineſſe, to be with Chriſt; and know aſſuredly they ſhall one day be with him in glory: yet they deſire to keep themſelves from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165632:7"/>the evil of the world ſo long as tis his pleaſure to continue them in it. Chriſt doth not pray his father to take us preſently out of the world, but to take the world, that is, the love of it out of us, and <hi>that we may be ſatisfied with the truth, verſ.</hi> 17. This ſhould be our deſire then, that whether preſent or abſent, <hi>we may be accepted of him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5 9.</note> That man therefore can have no true deſire to dye, that hath no deſire to live well: neither doth he deſire to have any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt after death, that doth not deſire it in his life: he that deſires to be with Chriſt after death, deſires alſo that Chriſt may be with him, and dwell in him before death. Theſe two deſires then are in effect one, ſaving that one is the perfections of the other; and in that regard the moſt deſirable. Theſe things premiſed, I now come to ſhew, why death may be deſired of us.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. It delivers us from manifold evils.</item>
               <item>2. It brings with it infinite good, to thoſe that are prepared for it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <label>1. Bodily evils.</label> The evils from which we are freed by death, <note place="margin">Quis enim ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit quantovis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquentiae flumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vitae hujus miſerias explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Auguſt. Eccleſ. 1.8. Verſtegan. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit. 58.</note> are either bodily evils, or ſoul evils, ſpirituall evils. For the firſt, bodily evils; even theſe, if I ſhould begin to ſpeak of them, they are more then I am able to expreſſe. All things are full of labour, man cannot utter it: What toile and labour are our bodies ſubject unto? What hardſhip do they here endure? Our old anceſtours, the Saxons, counted the ages of their lives by Winters; to ſhew how many ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of ſharp and cold weather they had overpaſt: beſides, how many diſeaſes are there incident to the frail bodies of men, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men! impoſtemes, ſwellings, agues, aches, apoplexies, ſtrangury, ſtone, gout, &amp;c. oh the ſtinging torment that is in ſome of theſe! I gave you an item indeed before, that none of theſe temporall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily evils ſhould cauſe us to deſire death, through impatience, or any repining diſpoſition; however, theres enough in them to wean us from this world, and to let us ſee the miſery of it: and death when it comes, it will free us from all theſe diſeaſes: when given by the hand of our heavenly Phyſician, 'tis the firſt phyſick that can be to cure us of them all. And as our bodies, ſo our eſtates likewiſe are ſubject to a thouſand changes: what loſſes and croſſes do we meet with there! as if a man be a rich man to day, he may be a beggar to morrow; if his eſtate lie in plate or money, thieves may break through and ſteal it; if in goods or houſhold-ſtuffe, they may likewiſe plunder him of all; if in houſes, the fire may conſume all; (how many Briefs tells us ſo?) if in lands, the rain may come and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165632:7"/>ſlocken all his fruit; if in merchandiſe, the ſea may ſwallow up all; if in cattell, the enemie, as the Sabeans did <hi>Jobs,</hi> may carry all away: and he may then ſit down and ſay as he, <hi>naked came I out of my mothers womb, and I ſee I ſhall return a naked man to the womb of the earth.</hi> I add here again, that a man muſt take heed of impatience, and diſcontent, otherwiſe I ſee no harme in it, if theſe changes mind him of his laſt change: and being thus ſtript and left naked, he begin to think of lying down to his reſt. Beſides this, many are the afflictions of the righteous,<note place="margin">Acerrimum par media mors diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. Seneca.</note> many are the wrongs they receive at the hands of wicked men: what cart-loads of reproches and diſgraces are they ready to caſt upon them? for there is an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy between the one and the other, as there is between fire and water, but when death comes, it ends the quarrell.</p>
            <p>
               <label>2. Spirituall evils.</label> But now for the ſecond, ſoul-evils, or ſpirituall evils, they are of far more force to draw on this deſire. The devil he is our conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall adverſary; and ſo long as we live here, ſo long will he be tempting us; he can no ſooner look into my heart, or thy heart, but he will ſee to what our natures and diſpoſitions are moſt inclind, and thereby he will work upon us.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.19.</note> Add hereunto that <hi>virus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum,</hi> that venome and poyſon of originall corruption, whereby we are diſabled from doing <hi>the good we would, and the evil we would not, that we do: The fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh, and theſe are contrary the one to the other:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> ſo that we cannot do the things that we would. <hi>Paul</hi> had a pitcht field, as it were, between himſelf and himſelf.<note place="margin">Velis, noli:; intra ſines tuos erit Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſaeus: prm. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, non extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari. Connatam habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus cupiditatem, haec puſſus eſt ut motus cordis, quem nemo mortalium in hac vita reprimit. Caſ. eth. Dan. 3.23. &amp; 25.</note> As <hi>Rebecca</hi> had the two twins ſtrugling in her womb: ſo in every regenerate man, theres the fleſh and ſpirit ſtrugling together; do what we can, this Jebuſite will ſtill be in our coaſts: The ſeeds of ſin may be in ſome meaſure ſuppreſt by the power of Gods ſpirit, but never rooted out till death: It is as the pulſe of a mans body, alwayes beating till then, but then it will ceaſe. Death will do no more to us, but what <hi>Nebuchadnezars</hi> fire did to the three children, it never toucht, nor harmd them, onely burnt their coards wherewith they were bound, and let them looſe: So death, when it comes, will looſe us from theſe coards and chains of our ſins, and ſet us at liberty: Therefore we ought to long after this full redemption. I remember what the Heathen did, they placed the Temple of reſt without the City, to ſhew, that if ever we would have tranquility and quietneſſe, it muſt be by going out of this world; then there will be no trouble or vexation of ſpirit, no concupiſcence, no ſin to withdraw us from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165632:8"/>God. Death came into the world by ſin, and ſin will not out of the world, but by death: God ſhall wipe away all tears from the eyes of his children, and then he ſaith, <hi>there ſhall be no more death,</hi> neither ſorrow,<note place="margin">Revel. 21.4.</note> nor crying, neither ſhall there be any more pain: Mark, God will firſt take away tears, and ſin, the cauſe of tears, that ſhall be covered with the garment of Chriſts righteouſneſſe: and then, as with a handkerchief, he will dry up their tears: he will firſt do away ſin from their ſouls, then twill be eaſie to wipe away tears from their eyes: it is ſin makes ſo many tears ſtand in the eyes of Gods children; therefore when ſin is once done away, all ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and tears, all crying and pains will ceaſe. Thus for the evils we ſhall be freed from. Now for the good, and benefit we ſhall be partakers of by death, and after: My text ſaith, <hi>We ſhall be with Chriſt,</hi> and that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>far better:</hi> If ſhall be far better then, then now in theſe four reſpects.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1.<note place="margin">Propter elonga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ſuam à conſuetudine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra &amp; a rebus ſeculi iſtius non eſt facile, &amp;c. Pariſ 696.</note> The Place of our habitation.</item>
               <item>2. Our Society and Company.</item>
               <item>3. Our Bodies: and</item>
               <item>4. In reſpect of our ſouls.</item>
            </list>
            <p>There is indeed a great elongation or eſtrangement between us, and things of eternity and that ſhall come to paſſe hereafter, by reaſon of our earthly mould and temper; let <hi>faith therefore which is the ſubſtance of things hoped for,</hi> here act, and ſtir up it ſelf, carrying us above our ſelves, and above our ſenſes, whileſt we are ſpeaking of theſe particulars. I begin with the Place.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> This world is a <hi>Sea of glaſſe: a Sea,</hi> for trouble; and <hi>glaſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Place. Rev. 15.2.</note> for brittleneſſe: it is <hi>a vale of miſery,</hi> as you have heard; but Heaven is <hi>a haven of reſt, a Paradiſe of pleaſures and delights.</hi> The earth is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an ill-favoured, dark, ſquallid, filthy place:<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19.</note> but in heaven is light inacceſſible. Now if a man that had lived in a dark cell or dungeon, ſhould be taken thence to live in ſome great and ſumptuous palace; he would think the world well amended: or if a man that had lived thirty or fourtie years in ſome mud-wall-Cottage in the countrey, ſhould change his dwelling, and live in the chiefeſt City of the Kingdome, and enjoy the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and riches of it, he would think himſelf a happier man then ever he was before:<note place="margin">Job 4.19.</note> We now dwell in <hi>houſes of clay, whoſe founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in the duſt;</hi> but the City of God is a moſt <hi>glorious City,</hi> the very <hi>gates of it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 21.10, 11.</note> Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>are of Pearl, and they that do his commandments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall enter in through the gates into the City.</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:165632:8"/>Oh how glorious ſhall things appear, when we ſhall come to the gates of that City! but when we ſhall paſſe through thoſe gates, how ſhall our ſouls be raviſht with joy, to ſee the things are there to be ſeen! The very <hi>ſtreets</hi> (he tels us) <hi>are of pure gold;</hi> But alas, What are Pearls? What is Gold? Indeed we ſee no better things here, and thats the reaſon the ſpirit of God ſets forth the glory of heaven by theſe things; otherwiſe they were not good enough to be compared, or worthy to be named the ſame day with heavens glory. And ſhould you imagine ſuch a City as he there deſcribes, whoſe gates were pearl, and ſtreets gold; the glory of it would not ſo far exceed the glory of the meaneſt village or hamlet, as the glory of heaven would ſurmount, and go beyond it. Think then with your ſelves, how deſirous a place heaven is. S. <hi>Peter,</hi> you know, when he was upon the holy Mount,<note place="margin">Mat. 17.4.</note> and beheld Chriſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured, was not his own man, but fell a talking of building Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, and I know not what: but, how would he have been raviſht, if himſelf had been transfigured, and tranſlated into the place of the Bleſſed! and S. <hi>Paul</hi> being rapt up thither, was not able,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.2.</note> of fourteen years after, to tell us, <hi>whether he was in the body, or out of the body,</hi> ſuch and ſo glorious is that place.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But what ſhall be our company there? not that which is now a vexation to our ſpirits, the company of ſwearers, drunkards, &amp;c. but of Angels, Patriarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Company.</note> 
               <hi>Oh praeclarum diem, cum in illud animorum concilium coetúmque pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiſcar, &amp; ex hac turba &amp; colluvione diſcedam!</hi> That is, Oh hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py day, when I ſhall depart out of this place of filth and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe, and go into that Synod of ſouls! an excellent ſaying to come out of the mouth of a Heathen. So let us ſay with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Oh when ſhall I come and appear in the preſence of God?</hi> and with <hi>Paul, When ſhall I enter into the City of the living God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.2.</note> the heavenly Jeruſalem? When ſhall I be amongſt that innumerable company of Angels, and that generall Aſſembly? When ſhall my ſoul be gathered to the <hi>ſouls of juſt men made perfect, and to Jeſus the Mediatour of the new Covenant?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.22.</note> Oh when ſhall I reſt in my center Chriſt Jeſus? when ſhall I be wholly his, and he be wholly mine? Oh this is our happineſſe to be with Chriſt, with him, who is <hi>the deſire of all Nations:</hi> with him, <hi>who ſuffered an accurſed death on the Croſſe, for our ſins:</hi> with him,<note place="margin">Joh. 17.24.</note> 
               <hi>whom our ſoule loveth:</hi> to be with him, and to behold the <hi>glory which the father hath given him:</hi> this is that ſhall make us happy for ever and ever.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:165632:9"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But all this, that is place, and company, ſeems to be but the happineſſe of the object; what ſhall be the happineſſe of the ſubject?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> It ſhall be in our bodies, and in our ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> For the body, it ſhall not then be ſubject to any change paſſion, or wearineſſe;<note place="margin">Body. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which are tour excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent properties of a glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Naz. orat. funebr. Mat. 26.41. Phil. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> it ſhall not be ſo dull and lumpiſh as now, but moſt agile and nimble: it ſhall not then ſtand in need of ſleep, meat and drink, which chain us ſo faſt by the teeth here. <hi>Now the ſpirit is ſometimes willing, but the fleſh is weak;</hi> our ſouls would fly up to heaven, but the fleſh clogs them and keeps them down: then it ſhall not be ſo, but the body as a ready and willing inſtrument ſhall follow the motions and deſires of the ſoul or ſpirit. <hi>The Lord ſhall change our vile bodie,</hi> or our body of humiliation, <hi>that it may be faſhioned and made like unto his glorious body: it is ſown in weakneſſe, raiſed again in power: it is ſown a naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it is raiſed a ſpirituall body:</hi> a body ſtill, but adorned with ſpirituall qualities. Now, will not faith cauſe us earneſtly to deſire a diſſolution (though nature ſhrink a little at the thought of it) when we ſhall conſider, that this mutable, ſinfull, corruptible, frail, and rotten tabernacle of our body ſhall be taken down, for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, but that by a bleſſed and glorious reſurrection, it may be reſtored, advanced, to perfect, firm, incorruptible, and celeſtiall glory?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, for our ſouls, how ſhall thoſe two faculties thereof, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and will,<note place="margin">Soul.</note> be then enobled! How perfect the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them! Our underſtandings ſhall be wonderfully irradiated, for the preſent they are blind and ignorant. let a man be never ſo ſtudious, and labour for knowledge with all his ſtrength; yet all he knows is but the leaſt part of what he is ignorant: <hi>For now we ſee through a glaſſe darkly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>but then face to face: now we know in part, but then we ſhall know even as we are known.</hi> The ſoul having been never ſo little a while in heaven, ſhall get more knowledge, then here it hath done in twenty or thirty years: <hi>For we ſhall then ſee him as he is.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.2.</note> So for our wills, what a ſweet conformity ſhall there be between them, and the will of God! <hi>We ſhall then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Lamb whereſoever he goeth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 24.4.</note> Now we follow him too, but 'tis but lamely, and 'tis not whereſoever he goeth; becauſe as we follow Chriſt, ſo the Devil follows us with his temptations, whereby we are drawn aſide and go aſtray. Oh, but then it ſhall not be ſo, but our wills ſhall be wholly conformable and obedient
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165632:9"/>to his bleſſed will, <hi>we ſhall follow him whereſoever he goeth.</hi> I have ſet before you the crown of life: I have truly, though imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly and very briefly, deſcribed the nature of our future happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. All is true that hath been ſaid; yet all that hath been ſaid, is nothing to the greatneſſe of it. You muſt remember that of the Apoſtle, <hi>The glory that ſhall be revealed in us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>it cannot be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by us,</hi> no not by the moſt enlarged underſtanding, but hereafter it ſhall be revealed in us. And this was it made <hi>Paul</hi> ſo deſirous of his diſſolution: as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> brings him in ſpeaking thus. <hi>I have taſted of the joyes of heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. to. 5. ad pop. Antioch. hom. 5.</note> 
               <hi>therefore delay is tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to me; I have had the firſt-fruits of the ſpirit, therefore I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the whole harveſt; I have been caught up into the third heavens and have ſeen the glory which is unutterable; I have beheld the ſplendor and glory of the court of heaven: Oh, I have learnt, I have learnt what good things I want the fruition of, ſtaying here: for this cauſe I ſigh, and groan within my ſelf, deſiring to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</hi> To ſumme up all, we ſee what reaſon there is, to make us deſire our diſſolution, whether we reſpect outward and bodily evils, or ſpirituall evils, the Devil, and our own corruptions joyning with him; and becauſe our ſanctification is imperfect here. The world is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a duſty, ſqualid, filthy place: no marvell, if the feet of our affections be ſtill gathering ſoyle, while we are walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it. And laſtly, becauſe our condition hereafter ſhall be far better then now it is, free from ſin and miſery; death will bring us to a far better eſtate, both for place, company, body and ſoul: even to ſuch happineſſe <hi>as eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, nor heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</hi> We can ſay no more,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note> but we ſhall know more when Chriſt ſhall ſay to us, <hi>Enter into thy Maſters joy:</hi> it cannot enter into us,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.21.</note> therefore we ſhall enter into it, and be filled with it.</p>
            <p>Now for application of this Doctrine, <hi>Death is a thing that may be deſired. I deſire</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, I may from hence ſhew you the dotage of the Papiſts, concerning Purgatory: they ſay mens ſouls muſt have a purgation there, before they come to heaven; and the pains of that place (ſome of them ſay) are as ſharp as the pains of hell, ſave onely <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that they are not ſo laſting: With what comfort then can a man deſire death, to go to ſuch a place? Nay, I have heard of ſome, whom this doctrine hath diſtracted, and they have fallen mad at the very thought of it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Chriſt tells the good
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165632:10"/>thief,<note place="margin">Luc, 23.43.</note> 
               <hi>to day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe. And I will</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that thoſe whom thou haſt given me be with me,<note place="margin">Joh. 17.24.</note> where I am:</hi> I hope they dare not ſay, that Chriſt is in Purgatory; he is not in <hi>limbo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 8.1.</note> but in <hi>olympo:</hi> not in <hi>purgatorio,</hi> but in <hi>empyreo,</hi> at the right hand of the throne of the Majeſty in the heavens, there is he in glory, and he will have us to be where he is, the text is plain.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the Scripture tells but of two places mens ſouls go to when they depart hence, heaven and hell: <hi>the beggar dyed,</hi> and his ſoul went, whither? to purgatory? no; but 'twas preſently recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into <hi>Abrahams boſome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 16 22.</note> that is, into heaven: and (ſaith the Text) the <hi>rich man alſo dyed, and was buried,</hi> and whether went his ſoul? to hell: the Text ſpeaks plainly, <hi>The rich man dyed, and was buried, and in hell,</hi> ſtayed no where by the way, but down to hell he went immediately. So in <hi>Matthew,</hi> he ſhall ſet the ſheep on his right hand, the goats on his left; at his right hand is the kingdome of heaven, at his left hand everlaſting fire: he that is not on his right hand, ſhall ſurely be on the left; therefore he that goes not into the kingdome of heaven, ſhall doubtleſſe go to hell, and fire everlaſting: the Scriptures tell not of any third place.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, the cloſe union of death, and Chriſts preſence, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws this dream of theirs: <hi>I deſire</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> here) <hi>to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and to be with Chriſt;</hi> there is no <hi>Medium</hi> between them. But enough of this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> In the ſecond place, it may teach us how to take the death of our friends;<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Weep not</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>as men without hope:</hi> theſe tears are unprofitable, they do our friends no good, but they may do us hurt. Conſider the neceſſitie of death; it cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided: all muſt dye: 'tis a debt our parents brought upon us, and muſt be paid, whenſoever it ſhall be required: and think likewiſe of the commonneſſe of death: 'tis as common a thing for men and women to dye, as to be born, and to go out of the world, as it is to come into the world: why then ſhould we wonder more at the one, then at the other? <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> when one came and told him his ſon was dead;<note place="margin">Spatio annorum 2256. compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henditur aetas quatuor partium qui à mundi ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordio hucuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerant. Nam &amp;c. Bucolch. chron. 224.</note> made him this Anſwer: I knew my ſon was mortall: as ſoon as I had begot him, I knew he ſhould die. Death now in our dayes is a very common thing; indeed, in the time between the Creation and the Flood, there was not a Coarſe to be ſeen, it may be, in two or three hundred years, they were then ſo long lived: but now with us, many hundreds dye, and depart
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165632:10"/>this world, every year, nay every week: ſeeing then others dye ſo faſt, what reaſon have we to think our friends ſhould be exempted, or why ſhould we be ſo full of grief,<note place="margin">Quid admiratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis meretur res, ſi ſciſſum eſt quod eratſciſſile, &amp; liquefactum quod eratliqueſi. &amp; ſi id crematum eſt quod erat u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile, &amp; ſi id per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iit, quod ita na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt ut poſſit perire? Plut de conſol. 185.</note> ſeeing death is ſo common a thing? What wonder is it to ſee trees conſume with age, wax melt, ſoluble things diſſolved, or to ſee frail mortals die that are born ſo, that they cannot but dye; is this any matter of wonder? But that which ſhould eſpecially qualifie our grief, is, from my text, and the doctrine delivered. Death is a thing to be deſired, then not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much lamented: we ſhould (I ſay) deſire, and do deſire it, as oft as we ſay the Lords Prayer, <hi>Thy Kingdome come.</hi> Therefore let us turn our ſorrow for the death of our friends, into a deſire of being with them in reſtand peace, when Gods good will and pleaſure is.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>3</label> Is death a thing deſirable? ſee here then the difference between the true Chriſtian, and the worldling. As it is with women, ſome have living births, and in their time they will come forth; others have dead births, and they ſtir not, but dye, and lye ſtill in the womb: ſo is it with men, ſome are dead, and they deſire to lye here ſtill; others have living births, are new born Chriſtians, and they cry out with <hi>Paul, Oh miſerable man that I am, who ſhall deliver me!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> they would fain be delivered, they long to be with Chriſt, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy his deſired preſence. As a man that hath ſores and ulcers on his body, and his ſhirt begins to cleave thereto, with what pain is it puld from his back? Even ſo is it with worldlings, whoſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are glewed to the earth, they are haled and puld from it, when they are to dye, as <hi>Joab</hi> was from the horns of the Altar. Oh death! how bitter is the remembrance of thee to a man that lives in his pleaſures? It is the King of terrours to ſuch men; when the thought of it comes into their minds, how doth it amaze and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them! <hi>Solomon</hi> deſcribing ſuch a man, ſaith, <hi>All his dayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus. 41.1. Eccl. 5.17. Foaming anger with or in his ſickneſſe. Pemb. in loc. Invenitur aliquis qui malit inter ſupplicia tabeſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp; perire mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratim, &amp; toties per ſtillicidiam amittere ani. mam, quàmſemel exhalare. Sen. 450. Epiſt.</note> 
               <hi>he eateth in darkneſſe, and he hath much ſorrow and wrath with his ſickneſſe,</hi> becauſe he is loth to depart, unwilling to leave this world. As it was with the Gibeonites, they were content to be hewers of wood, drawers of water, rather then depart from the tents of the Iſraelites: So theſe men had rather do any thing here, endure any drudgery, then depart out of this world; had rather conſume in the midſt of torments, have their ſouls drop away in drops, and all the members of their bodies periſh one after another; then dye and leave the world.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Oh Sir, but life is ſweet:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> What life do you mean? for this we live here, hardly deſerves
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165632:11"/>the name of life: for, how can we call that life, where heat ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, cold pincheth, meats and drinks make us dull and heavie, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weakens us, humours ſwell us up, old age buckles us together, ſhrinks our ſinews, wrinckles our skins, dimms our ſight, ratling phlegme riſes up and choaks us, and at laſt, death ſeizeth upon us! What a life is this?<note place="margin">Oh vita non vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</note> Oh wretched life that tendeth to death! Let us therefore be in love with that life which death brings us unto, for that is life indeed. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Our life is hid with Chriſt in God:</hi> the Saints aſpire after this life, and they have their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wafted up to heaven, and this, to them, is all in all. When Chriſt is here preſent, ſometimes in his ordinances, what comfort do they find herein! But how much greater will it be hereafter, when we ſhall ſee him as he is! As a woman is glad of a Letter from her husband, but more deſirous of the company of her husband: ſo it may comfort us a little, that we hear from him, and that God ſends his Miniſters, and ſervants to us, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſent <hi>Timothy</hi> to the Theſſalonians,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>to comfort us concerning our faith;</hi> that he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give us his holy word, which is as it were a letter ſent us from heaven: Oh, but how much greater will our joy and happineſſe be, when we ſhall be with Chriſt, enjoy his deſired preſence, and follow him whereſoever he goeth! Now then, what terrour do we find in death? or for what need we to fear it? for it ſhall then come to us, as an officer comes to an heir, giving him poſſeſſion of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance: So, death is no more but Gods officer, to bring us into the poſſeſſion of the Kingdome of Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> Therefore in the laſt place, let it teach us to labour to get <hi>Pauls</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; let us deſire thus, that we may deſire death: Its a great heighth this, and God ſometimes will not give his children ſo great a deſire as at other times, therefore labour thou to come to this, which that thou mayſt the better do, conſider theſe helps to further thee herein.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, becauſe contraries are oft cured by contraries, too much love of this bodily life,<note place="margin">Dulcedo divini amoris carnalis amoris ſuavita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem procul ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellit. Divinae dilectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis fervor inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè ardens affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiones omnes externas quaſi paleas abſumit. Comp. ſper. doct. 198.</note> with the love of the ſpirituall life, too much affecting of earthly things, with the love of heavenly; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore raiſe up thy ſelf to conſider the excellency of heaven, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things, and then earthly things will ſeem leſſe: as a man on the top of a high mountain, or tower, ſees men below like crowes. I remember a pleaſant relation in <hi>Scipio</hi>'s dream, how that when he, as he thought, was taken up into heaven amongſt his friends <hi>Paulus</hi> and <hi>Affricanus,</hi> and they ſhewed him the motion of the Planets, and the greatneſſe of the Celeſtiall Orbs; he caſt his eyes down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165632:11"/>the earth which ſeemd but like a Tennis-ball, &amp; ſearching to find out the place where his kingdome lay, it was ſo ſmall he could ſcarce diſcern it: But as he was thus poaring on the ground,<note place="margin">Coeleſtia ſemper ſpectato, illa hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana contemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> 
               <hi>Affricanus</hi> puls him by the ſleeve, and bid him mind heavenly things, and not to regard earthly; for what is it (ſaith he) to have a name upon earth? ſay thou hadſt Carthage, and all Numantia; yet cannot thy name fly over this Caucaſus, nor ſwim over this Ganges: Thou ſeeſt how ſmall a thing the earth is, and that ſea, (pointing to the Atlantick.) which ye call the great ſea and the main ocean, which though it have ſo great a name, thou ſeeſt how ſmall a thing it is. This was but a Philoſophers dream, yet 'cis pleaſant to conſider how far thoſe men went. Let us that are Chriſtians, ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the excellency of heaven, and vanity of earthly things; let us mount aloft upon the wings of divine contemplation, and our mindes being there, all things here below will be as nothing to us. <hi>Seek thoſe things</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that are above,</hi> or on high: What? where the Orbs and Planets are? No, higher then ſo:<note place="margin">Col. 3.2.</note> where Angels and Arch-angels are? No, higher yet, where <hi>Chriſt ſits on the right hand of God.</hi> Oh if the ſoul of any here preſent were, with <hi>Paul,</hi> rapt up into the third heavens, to be there but one hour, to ſee what he ſaw; how would he be ready to trample theſe things under his feet, as vile and deſpicable! he would count them traſh in compariſon of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as dung to that pearl.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It may be ſaid, all this is but matter of ſpeculation; therefore in the ſecond place, Give thy ſelf to the practiſe of mortification, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have all things mortified unto thee, then thou wilt not care ſo much for them. Offer what yee will to a dead man, he regards it not: So let us labour to get our affections, whether covetous, or pleaſurable, mortified; and we ſhall not care for theſe things. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie therefore your members which are upon earth, fornication, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, inordinate affection, evil concupiſcence, and covetouſneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> Indeed, this mortification of all evil affections is a hard work: for as it is with men that have ſtrong bodies, and ſuffer violent deaths; you ſee what a lamentable conflict there is, what ſtrugling between life and death, and when you think the man quite dead, a good while after, he gives a great ſigh or groan, nature then gathering all her ſtrength to withſtand death, flying as it were in the very face of death, either to vanquiſh, or to be overcome: Even thus it is, if we go about to take away the life of our deareſt luſts, they will gather all the forces they can either make of themſelves, or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165632:12"/>and the world can ſupply them withall, to ſtand before them, and defend them, that we may not come at them; but if for all that, we break through, and ſmite them ſo that we give them their deaths-wound, yet they will gather ſtrength again, and riſe up to hurt us, and do us a miſchief afterwards. Oh, 'tis hard, 'tis hard, and many a Chriſtian is forced even with tears in his eyes to cry out to heaven for help when he is at this work, yet this yee ſee, is that we are<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 5.24: Rom. 6.6.8.13.</note> calld to, that which every regenerate man and woman ſets him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to: and he who hath in good earneſt ſet himſelf to it, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured the mortifying of his ſins, will not be afraid of death; but rather ſee great cauſe why he ſhould deſire it: whatſoever pains it brings, he is provided for it, and may ſay thus: <hi>Oh death, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard not any ſting, thou canſt ſting my body withall; for, ſin thy worſt ſting, wherewith thou wouldeſt ſting my ſoul to death, is in ſome meaſure mortified and ſubdued by the power of Gods Spirit: that conflict thou art now about to bring upon my body, will be but ſhort to that I have endured in my ſoul theſe ſo many years. Oh wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come death, come, do thine office: I have been endeavouring a long time the death of my ſins, and ſomething through the power and mercy of God I have done; though not ſo much as I would: come, lend me thy hand to finiſh this work. I have oft ſmote my ſins, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to lay them in the duſt; yet they have riſen again: one ſtroke now of thy hand will cauſe them to dye, that they ſhall never riſe up any more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, let us think oft, and conſider what our condition is while we are here ſubject to ſin and miſery: do what we can, we cannot ſo mortifie ſin that it ſhall not be in us:<note place="margin">Non hîc ſumus ſine peccato, fed exibimus ſine peccato. Aug.</note> its true, the old man hath received his deaths wound in every regenerate man, and is bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out his life by degrees, and at death ſhall quite expire, and bleed his laſt, but not till then: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf, <hi>I find a law in my members, warring againſt the law of my mind; who ſhall deliver me from this body of death?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.23, 24.</note> or, oh that I were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from it! There will be a body of ſin and death in us, ſo long as we carry this body of earth and fleſh about us: this is plain then, as long as we live here, we ſhall ſin; and what Chriſtian deſires to live to ſin, and to offend God! Oh ye that love the Lord, hate ſin (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>hate that which is evil.</hi> We ſhould therefore deſire it for this cauſe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 97.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, let us oft look at death: <hi>Plato</hi> ſaid, that the life of a Philoſopher ſhould be nothing elſe, but a meditation of death, much
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165632:12"/>more, the life of a Chriſtian. It was a cuſtome amongſt the Greek Emperours, a Stone-cutter came to the Emperour on the day of his Coronation, preſented divers ſtones before him, and deſired to know of him, which of thoſe ſtones he would have for his Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre. And I have read of a people, who at their feaſts were wont to drink to one another out of dead-mens skuls, to mind them of death. <hi>Joſeph</hi> of Arimathea, who brought the Goſpel hither into England, he had his ſepulchre hewn out of a rock,<note place="margin">Joh. 19.41.</note> ſtanding ready for him in his garden: So let us, when the world ſeems to crown us with its chiefeſt delights, then remember death: when we eat and drink, think we ſee death on our tables; when we are in our private Gardens, then alſo let us take a turn with death, and let us act death before it comes: As a man that would fain fall aſleep, ſhuts his eyes, draws the curtains, layes his head to the pillow, and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth himſelf to ſleep: ſo do thou; oft think with thy ſelf in what manner death will ſurpriſe thee, look at it before it comes, and it will be the eaſier when it comes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And laſtly, as we muſt look at it, ſo we muſt alſo look beyond it: indeed it is a terrible thing to look at death, but caſt thine eye now beyond it, and there will be no terrour in it. Think of <hi>Paul</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, how it will be far better with us then, then now; in regard of Place, Company, our Bodies, and our Soules. But indeed (as I noted to you before) that glory is unſpeakable. As the Queen of Sheba ſaid of <hi>Solomons</hi> glory, She heard a great deal, yet not half of it was told her: the ſame may we ſay of eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that, we cannot declare half of it unto you: meditate we may, and ought, of that glory; yet this we muſt know, that we come exceeding far ſhort. This therefore ſhould make us go with as great deſire to the grave, as they uſe to go to a marriage; becauſe then, we ſhall be married to Chriſt Jeſus: And as Travellers, when the day is well ſpent, and the Sun grows low, come chearfully into their Inns at night: ſo ſhould we, to this common Inne of Death.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
